Guide to the Gibbs Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Gibbs family papers
1718-1893
MS 236
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.25
(1 box, 1 folio)
Correspondence, financial papers and memorabilia of members of the Gibbs family. Of principal interest are thirteen letters (1783-1796) from Roger Sherman to his brother-in-law, Henry Gibbs, of which five (1789-1790) discuss the deliberations of the first Congress of the United States. Other figures represented in the papers are two Josiah Willard Gibbses (father and son) and Addison Van Name.
Gibbs family
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Gibbs Family Papers are housed in a single box (15 folders) and one folio and span the dates 1718 to 1893. The papers contain a variety of materials from legal documents and correspondence to tax papers and a poem.
The most interesting letters are found in folders 3 and 4, thirteen letters from Connecticut statesman Roger Sherman to his brother-in-law Henry Gibbs, a Salem, Massachusetts merchant. Many of the letters concern business matters. Five, however, written by Sherman between 1789 Jun 1 and 1790 Jun 10 discuss the activities of the first Congress of the United States. The papers also contain three letters written by Roger Sherman, Jr. to his uncle and aunt.
Other items of possible interest include a letter from Yale Professor of Sacred Literature Josiah W. Gibbs to the Reverend Isaac N. Tarbox (1815-1888) recommending William C. Shipman; an 1852 agreement between Gibbs and William C. Fowler (1793-1881), author of a well known three volume series of English grammers, on Gibbs' participation in this project; and a poem, "The Storm," written in 1893 by the famous scientist J. Willard Gibbs. See the Genealogical Chart for an outline of the relationships among the persons represented in this collection.
The eighteenth century material in the Gibbs Family Papers, folders 1-4, was donated to Yale University in 1942 by Theodora, Ralph Gibbs, and Willard Gibbs Van Name, "The Storm" was given by A. Guyot Cameron, and the remaining items were purchased.
Note: Mary (Shrimpton) Gibbs, Henry Gibbs, and Mary (Gibbs) Cotton do not belong to the Gibbs family line of the Reverend Henry Gibbs (1668-1723) and Henry Gibbs (1709-1759).
Biographical / Historical
Roger Sherman, 1721-1793: Connecticut statesman, delegate to the Continental Congress, 1774-1781, signer and delegate to Constitutional Convention, 1783-1784, Congressman, 1789-1791; Senator, 1791-1793. Josiah Willard Gibbs, 1790-1861: orientalist, philologist, teacher, librarian Yale, 1824-1843, Professor of Sacred Literature, Yale, 1826-1861. Josiah Willard Gibbs, 1839-1903: mathematician, physicist, Professor of Mathematical Physics, Yale, 1871-1903. Addison Van Name, 1835-1922: librarian, philologist, librarian, Yale, 1865-1905.
For a chart outlining the genealogical relations of the Gibbs family, please consult the Genealogical Chart.
Families; Science; United States -- History -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775; Deeds; Educators; Legislators; Politicians; Fowler, William Chauncey, 1793-1881; Gibbs, Henry, 1668-1723; Gibbs, Henry, 1749-1794; Gibbs, J. Willard (Josiah Willard), 1839-1903; Gibbs, Josiah W. (Josiah Willard), 1790-1861; Sherman, Roger, 1721-1793; Sherman, Roger, 1768-1856; Tarbox, Increase N. (Increase Niles), 1815-1888; Van Name, Addison, 1835-1922; Gibbs family; United States. Congress
- Inventory
  - Legal papers, 1721, 1747 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Legal papers, 1761, 1765 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1783-1789 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1790-1796 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1851, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Agreement, 1852 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Estate papers of Josiah W. Gibbs, 1861-1862 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Taxes, 1861-1866 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Treasury certificates, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Josiah W. Gibbs: notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - J. Willard Gibbs: notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "The Storm" by J. Willard Gibbs, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Addison Van Name: valedictory address, 1858 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Addison Van Name: printed material and memorabilia from German universities, 1859-1860 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Addison Van Name: subscription, 1873 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Gibbs, Mary (Shrimpton). Deed signed and sealed by her son Henry Gibbs (1694-1761), "braisier" of Boston, for land in Boston, 1718 February 25 (Box CF15)
  - Gibbs, Henry (1668-1723). Articles of division and partition of property with Henry Gibbs (1694-1761), 1721 May 8 (Box CF15)
  - Gibbs, Mary (Shrimpton). Deed signed and sealed from Mary Gibbs and her son-in-law and daughter, John and Mary (Gibbs) Cotton, to her son Henry Gibbs (1694-1761) for land in Boston, 1721 May 25 (Box CF15)
  - Van Name, Addison. Certificate from University of Halle, 1859 Nov 11. (Box CF15)
  - Van Name, Addison. Certificate from University of Tübingen, 1860 May 20 (Box CF15)